Finding Aid for the The Noel Polk/Andrew Lytle Collection
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
The Noel Polk/Andrew Lytle Collection
2005
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
MSS.0339
.84 linear feet
Summary
Size 2 Linear Feet
Geographic Locations United States
Inclusive Dates 1925-1971
Bulk Dates 1968-1970
Languages English
Summary This collection contains the working papers of Noel Polk (1943 -), a literary scholar whose areas of specializations include: American literature, Southern writers, and Bibliographies. The materials housed in this collection relate to Polk’s published work from the Fall 1970 Mississippi Quarterly titled: “Andrew Nelson Lytle: A Bibliography of His Writings.”
Access Restrictions No Restrictions
Copyright Rights are retained by Special Collections, Vanderbilt University.
Stack Locations Manuscripts
BIOGRAPHICAL/HISTORICAL NOTE
1943 Born in Picayune, Mississippi on February 23 rd.
1965 Received Bachelor of Arts from Mississippi College
1966 Received Masters of Arts from Mississippi College
1967 Married on January 27 th to Patricia Parrott, they later divorced in 1990.
1970 Obtained Ph.D. from the University of South Carolina – Columbia. Published “Andrew Nelson Lytle: A Bibliography of His Writings” in Mississippi Quarterly.
1970-1974 Assistant professor of English at the University of Texas at Arlington.
1974-1976 Visiting associate research professor and bibliographer in Southern Studies Program at the University of South Carolina at Columbia.
1976-1977 Independent researcher.
1977-1979 Assistant professor of English at the University of Southern Mississippi, Hattiesburg.
1979-1981 Received grant from National Endowment for the Humanities.
1979-1983 Associate professor of English at the University of Southern Mississippi, Hattiesburg.
1981-1982 Professeur Associe. at the University of Strasbourg.
1983-- Professor of English at the University of Southern Mississippi, Hattiesburg.
1986-1989 Received grant from National Endowment for the Humanities.
1991 Received grant from National Endowment for the Humanities.
1994-1995 Received grant from National Endowment for the Humanities.
2005 Fulbright Senior Scholar at the University of Lodz, Poland.
SCOPE AND CONTENT NOTE
In 1985, Special Collections at the Jean and Alexander Heard Library acquired a collection of working papers from Noel Polk on his bibliography of Andrew Nelson Lytle. The Noel Polk/Andrew Lytle Collection was a generous donation made by Mr. Polk himself.
This collection contains the working papers of Noel Polk, a literary scholar whose areas of specializations include: American literature, Southern writers, and Bibliographies. The materials housed in this collection relate to Polk’s published work from the Mississippi Quarterly titled: “Andrew Nelson Lytle: A Bibliography of His Writings.”
The basis for Noel Polk’s bibliography of Andrew Lytle stemmed from the Society for the Study of Southern Literature. The Society was created in 1967 to develop research tools to aid in the study of American Southern writers. The Society commissioned the Mississippi Quarterly, the Journal of Southern Cultures, to create a Bibliography Committee that would compile an ongoing bibliography of all books and articles about and by southern writers. Polk’s work is included in the Fall 1970 issue of the Mississippi Quarterly.
The Noel Polk/Andrew Lytle Collection consists of three boxes, one of which is oversize. The materials within this collection have been arranged in the following series: Correspondence, Research Materials, and Writings.
SERIES AND SUBSERIES DESCRIPTIONS
Series I. Correspondence, 1925-1971 (0.5 boxes)
The Correspondence Series is made up of both incoming and outgoing letters. In order to maintain original order the incoming letters have been kept as they were, with the initial outgoing letter paper-clipped together. The correspondence has thus been arranged chronologically by the date of the initial outgoing letter. An interesting note, included within this series is a letter from the U.S. Senator Strom Thurmond that bears his signature. Most correspondence concerns Noel Polk obtaining information for his bibliography of Andrew Lytle’s works.
Series II. Research Material, [1968-1971] (1 box)
This series contains various materials used by Mr. Polk for his research when writing the bibliography. Included within the material are notes, correspondence, copies of Lytle’s writings, reviews of Lytle’s writings, and a notebook of notes for the bibliography. Arrangement?
Series III. Writings, Undated (0.5 box and 1 oversize box)
The Writings Series consists of typescripts, galley proofs, and a checklist of Polk’s “Andrew Nelson Lytle: A Bibliography of His Writings.” Some documents are marked while some have been left unmarked. This series contains oversize material.
- Series I. Correspondence
  - Correspondence, 1925-1951 (Box 1, Folder 1.)
  - Correspondence, June 8, 1968 – Aug. 25, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 2.)
  - Correspondence, Sept. 3, 1969 – Oct. 31, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 3.)
  - Correspondence, Nov. 1, 1969 – Nov. 25, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 4.)
  - Correspondence, Dec. 1, 1969 – Dec. 22, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 5.)
  - Correspondence, Jan. 4, 1970 – Feb. 23, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 6.)
  - Correspondence, March 12, 1970 – Feb. 25, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 7.)
  - Correspondence, Notes and fragments [1968-1971] (Box 1, Folder 8.)
- Series II. Research Material
  - Research Material: Copy of Andrew Lytle’s short story “Alchemy” (Box 1, Folder 9.)
  - Research Material: Copies of Andrew Lytle’s Bedford Forrest and His Critter Company (1 of 3) (Box 1, Folder 10.)
  - Research Material: Copies of Andrew Lytle’s Bedford Forrest and His Critter Company (2 of 3) (Box 1, Folder 11.)
  - Research Material: Copies of Andrew Lytle’s Bedford Forrest and His Critter Company (3 of 3) (Box 1, Folder 12.)
  - Research Material: Copy of Andrew Lytle’s A Christian University and The Word (Box 1, Folder 13.)
  - Research Material: Copy of Andrew Lytle’s short story “The Guide” (Box 1, Folder 14.)
  - Research Material: Copy of Andrew Lytle’s short story “Jericho, Jericho, Jericho” (Box 1, Folder 15.)
  - Research Material: Copy of Andrew Lytle’s short story “Mister MacGregor” (Box 1, Folder 16.)
  - Research Material: Notes for Lytle’s A Name For Evil, 1947 (1 of 2) (Box 1, Folder 17.)
  - Research Material: Notes for Lytle’s A Name For Evil, 1947 (2 of 2) (Box 1, Folder 18.)
  - Research Material: Copy of Andrew Lytle Letters (1936-1938) (Box 1, Folder 19.)
  - Research Material: Copies of Lytle’s Periodical Articles (1 of 2) (Box 1, Folder 20.)
  - Research Material: Copies of Lytle’s Periodical Articles (2 of 2) (Box 1, Folder 21.)
  - Research Material: Reviews of Andrew Lytle works (Box 1, Folder 22.)
  - Research Material: Notes (Box 1, Folder 23.)
  - Research Material: Notes on Andrew Lytle’s Hero with the Private Parts (1966) (Box 1, Folder 24.)
  - Research Material: Notes – Andrew Lytle’s The Long Night (1936) (Box 1, Folder 25.)
  - Research Material: Notes on Lytle’s At The Moon’s Inn (1941) (1 of 2) (Box 1, Folder 26.)
  - Research Material: Notes on Lytle’s At The Moon’s Inn (1941) (2 of 2) (Box 1, Folder 27.)
  - Research Material: Notes on Andrew Lytle’s Novel, Novella, 4 stories (1958) (Box 1, Folder 28.)
  - Research Material: Notes on Lytle’s The Velvet Horn (1957) (Box 1, Folder 29.)
  - Research Material: Notes on Lytle’s unpublished poems, stories, plays, and essays (Box 2, Folder 1.)
  - Research Material: Notes and copies of Lytle’s Sewanee Review articles – Hero comparisons ( 1 of 4) (Box 2, Folder 2.)
  - Research Material: Notes and copies of Lytle’s Sewanee Review articles – Hero comparisons ( 2 of 4) (Box 2, Folder 3.)
  - Research Material: Notes and copies of Lytle’s Sewanee Review articles – Hero comparisons ( 3 of 4) (Box 2, Folder 4.)
  - Research Material: Notes and copies of Lytle’s Sewanee Review articles – Hero comparisons ( 4 of 4) (Box 2, Folder 5.)
  - Research Material: Andrew Lytle Secondary Sources (1 of 2) (Box 2, Folder 6.)
  - Research Material: Andrew Lytle Secondary Sources (2 of 2) (Box 2, Folder 7.)
  - Research Material: Andrew Lytle Checklist for University of Mississippi Press Book (Box 2, Folder 8.)
  - Research Material: Notebook for Andrew Lytle Bibliography (Box 2, Folder 9.)
- Series III. Writings
  - Writings: Andrew Lytle Bibliography – Typescript (1 of 5) (Box 2, Folder 10.)
  - Writings: Andrew Lytle Bibliography – Typescript (2 of 5) (Box 2, Folder 11.)
  - Writings: Andrew Lytle Bibliography – Typescript (3 of 5) (Box 2, Folder 12.)
  - Writings: Andrew Lytle Bibliography – Typescript (4 of 5) (Box 2, Folder 13.)
  - Writings: Andrew Lytle Bibliography – Typescript (5 of 5) (Box 2, Folder 14.)
  - Writings: An Andrew Lytle Checklist (Box 2, Folder 15.)
  - Writings: Galley proof – Andrew Nelson Lytle: A Bibliography of His Writings (1 of 2) (Box 2, Folder 16.)
  - Writings: Galley proof – Andrew Nelson Lytle: A Bibliography of His Writings (2 of 2) (Box 2, Folder 17.)
  - Writings: Andrew Lytle’s Bibliography – First corrected galleys (Box 2, Folder 18.)
  - Writings: Andrew Lytle Bibliography – Second Corrected Galley (Box 2, Folder 1.)
  - Writings: Andrew Lytle Bibliography – Marked Galley (Box 2, Folder 2.)
  - Writings: Andrew Lytle Bibliography – Marked Galley Mississippi Quarterly (Box 2, Folder 3.)
  - Writings: Andrew Lytle Bibliography – Marked Galley Mississippi Quarterly (Box 2, Folder 4.)
  - Writings: Andrew Lytle Bibliography – Marked Galley (Box 2, Folder 5.)
  - Writings: Andrew Lytle Bibliography – Marked Galley (Box 2, Folder 6.)
  - Writings: Andrew Lytle Bibliography – Marked Galley (Box 2, Folder 7.)
  - Writings: Andrew Lytle Bibliography – Unmarked Galley Proof (Box 2, Folder 8.)
  - Writings: Andrew Lytle Bibliography – Marked Galley Mississippi Quarterly (Box 2, Folder 9.)